What are you thinking about?
想什么呢
Nothing.
没想什么
Why do I smell something burning?
我怎么闻到有东西糊了
My dish!
我的菜
Did something happen?
发生什么事了吗
Qianqian wants to invite you to be her husband.
浅姐邀你当她夫婿
What?
什么
She sees a good catch and now she wants to snatch him away, huh?
这是看到肉肥都来抢来了
No, she means to "borrow" him.
是借 借
To drive away a customer who's been harassing her.
为了赶走骚扰她的客人
That won't work, either.
借也不成啊
Dear, why are you pulling me?
老头子 你拉我干吗
If a woman wanted to borrow you from me,
要是有女人跟我借你
would you be okay with it?
你乐意啊
Well, if she were gentle, I guess I wouldn't mind.
那要是温柔一点也不是不行
Say that again! I dare you!
你再说 再说你
What kind of reward did she offer
她给了你什么好处啊
that you'd sell me out just for a few taels of silver?
你花几两银子就把我给卖了
How could I possibly sell you out for just a few taels?
我怎么可能几两银子就把你卖了
Yeah, exactly.
是啊 是啊
A few taels do sound a bit too cheap.
几两是便宜了点
Thirty taels.
三十两
-What? -Thirty taels?
什么 三十两
Well, Changyu means well, after all.
说来长玉这丫头也是一片好心
Yan Zheng, why don't you just help out?
言正 要不然你就帮个忙
Think of it as doing a good deed.
就当作积德行善了
Hey, wait...
不是
What? Why "hey, wait?"
你诶 诶什么诶
If you could sell for even 3 or 5 taels,
要是你能卖个三五两
I'd agree immediately.
我立马答应
You...
你
Changning.
长宁
Let's go. Let's ignore them.
走 咱们不理他们了
Turns out I'm worth even less than a pig.
大叔还不如头猪值钱呢
And how much do you think you're worth?
你以为你值多少钱呢
Why don't you ask someone else?
你怎么不去求别人啊
Like that... Lord Li or whatever.
比如那个什么 李大人
Well, he's not in Lin'an.
他不在林安哪
Even if he were, I wouldn't ask him.
他就算在我也不会求他的
I've got my own husband—
自己夫婿不求
why go to an outsider?
求一个外人干吗
Just help Qianqian out.
你就帮帮浅姐嘛
It's just for 1 day.
就一天
If her Yixiang Restaurant goes under,
她那溢香楼倒了
our business will suffer as well.
咱们买卖也不好做呀
That rice merchant surnamed Qi
那姓齐的米商
clings to her like a stubborn bandage.
就是个狗皮膏药
He's just impossible to get rid of.
黏上了甩都甩不掉
Harmless, but irritating.
不害人但膈应人
The rice merchant surnamed Qi?
姓齐的米商
Who has he been associating with lately?
最近他可与何人过从甚密
It's said to be a rice merchant from the Capital, surnamed Qi.
说是京城来的米商姓齐
Just for 1 day?
就一天
This way, please.
这边请
Zheng.
妹夫
In this outfit, let alone a restaurant manager—
你这一身莫说是个掌柜
you could even pass for a marquis.
就说是个侯爷都有人信
Not bad. This way, please.
不错 这边请
I'm counting on you today.
今日就靠你了
Rest assured.
放心吧
Changyu said
长玉说了
you're her best friend in Lin'an.
你是她在林安最好的朋友
If she wants to help you,
她想帮你的话
I'll do it without hesitation.
我定会义无反顾
This way.
这边
Mr. Qi.
齐公子
Manager Yu, are you feeling better?
俞掌柜 你的病好了
Mr. Qi, this is my husband, Yan Zheng.
齐公子 这位是我夫婿言正
He's been away on business recently.
近日啊 他一直在外地办事
He just returned to Lin'an today,
今日才回林安
and I brought him here specifically
我特意带他过来
to thank you for supporting our humble restaurant's business.
感谢您照顾我们小店生意
Mr. Qi.
齐公子
Pleasure to meet you.
幸会
So you're Manager Yu's husband.
你就是俞掌柜的夫婿
Naturally.
自然
Yan Zheng, have a good chat with Mr. Qi.
言正 你同齐公子好生聊
I'll go prepare some food and wine.
我去备些酒菜
Mr. Qi.
齐公子
Please.
请
When Master throws his cup as a signal,
听主子掷杯为号
that's our cue to tie that guy up.
就把人绑了
I heard you came from the Capital, Mr. Qi.
听闻齐公子是从京城而来
I wonder why you've come to our tiny Lin'an Town
不知为何到我们这小小的林安镇
for grain business?
来做粮食生意
Mr. Yan, you're not a local here either.
言公子亦不是本籍人
So why are you running a restaurant here in Lin'an?
为何会在这林安做酒楼生意啊
My wife may not have attended to things properly.
内子照顾不周
Please bear with us, Mr. Qi.
还请公子担待
Next time there's business,
往后有什么买卖
please come straight to me.
找我即可
It's just I wonder how big a deal you can handle, Mr. Yan.
不知道言公子能做多大的买卖
For example...
比如
200,000 piculs of grain.
二十万石粮食
Pardon me.
失礼了
With our Yixiang Restaurant doing so well,
我们这溢香楼生意太过火爆
it's inevitable that some jealous rivals
难免会有一些红眼的对家
cause trouble in the dark.
暗中作乱
No wonder Manager Yu
难怪俞掌柜
turned down my request to book the whole place earlier.
拒绝了齐某的包场之请
Apparently, my business wasn't enough to interest you guys.
原来是买卖不够大
Alright then.
好
Let's talk another day.
那我们改日再聊
Where is he?
人呢
Gone.
走了
He gave up just like that?
这么简单就放弃了
Zheng.
妹夫
My 30 taels were really well spent.
我这三十两花得可真值啊
What happened, Master?
主子这是怎么了
You won't believe it—
你绝对想不到
I just ran into a dead man,
孤刚刚遇到一个死人
and that woman actually claimed he was her husband.
那女人居然说是她的夫君
Master, you mean...
主子指的是
Marquis of Wu'an, Xie Zheng.
武安侯 谢征
Xie Zheng?
谢征
Isn't he dead?
他不是死了吗
If the Marquis of Wu'an is still alive,
倘若武安侯尚在人间
I'm afraid Lord Changxin's plan won't go smoothly.
只怕长信王的计策不便于行啊
That smart father of mine
孤的那位好父王
intended to use the move of bandits stealing military grain
本想凭借着山贼抢军粮这步棋后
to drive out refugees and create panic,
赶流民 造恐慌
and then finish the operation.
最后收网
But now,
可如今
not only is the Marquis of Wu'an not dead,
武安侯不但没死
but he even knows we purchased 200,000 piculs of grain.
还知道我们买了二十万石粮
Obviously, he's been prepared all along.
显然他早有准备
It's still hard to say who will win in the end.
鹿死谁手尚未可知
This game is getting more and more interesting.
这场戏真是越来越有趣了
Back then, you intentionally leaked information, Master,
当初主子故意放出风声
to lead the Marquis of Wu'an to investigate
引武安侯去查
the Jinzhou Massacre from 16 years ago
十六年前的瑾州惨案
because you believed Prime Minister Wei wouldn't allow him to reopen the case.
就是料定魏相不会让他翻案
Your plan was to use Prime Minister Wei
想借魏相之手
to get rid of that serious threat Xie Zheng.
除掉谢征这一心腹大患
But now, he's still alive...
可如今他还活着
Should we reveal his whereabouts
咱们要不要把他的行踪
to Wei Yan in secret
偷偷告诉魏严
and try to get Wei Yan to do the dirty work for us again?
再来一次借刀杀人
No.
不
I tried to turn them against each other back then
当初引他们反目
just to sever Wei Yan's support.
就是为了断掉魏严的臂膀
The Marquis of Wu'an has never been our enemy.
武安侯与我们从来就不是敌人
Now that the rift between uncle and nephew is a done deal,
如今既然舅甥二人反目已成定局
and the Marquis of Wu'an has been cast out to the countryside,
武安侯又流落乡野
we can take this opportunity to win him over.
我们可以借机拉拢
Take my East Palace seal and use my former identity
你拿着我的东宫大印
as the Crown Prince of the Eastern Palace to lure him in.
借用前东宫身份引他上钩
Got it.
是
As for Manager Yu...
那俞掌柜那边
Her?
她
Just have someone keep a close eye on her.
找人盯紧便是
Come on in, ladies. This way.
来两位 里面请
Please come in, ladies.
客官 里面请
Welcome, ladies.
里面请 客官
Mrs. Fan.
樊娘子
Changyu.
长玉
Come here.
过来
Look.
你看看
The restaurant is so lively—
这楼里这么热闹
it's all thanks to you.
可都是沾了你的光
What do you mean, thanks to me?
沾我什么光啊
Ever since your husband came by,
自从你那夫婿来了一趟溢香楼
that Qi fellow hasn't bothered me again.
那姓齐的就再也没有骚扰过我
I can finally focus on running the business.
我也有心照顾生意了
Now look—the restaurant is so lively.
楼里这么热闹
Of course it's thanks to you.
可不是沾了你的光
Come with me.
你跟我过来
I wonder what Chef Li is cooking for New Year's Eve.
也不知道李大厨除夕做了什么菜
What are you planning to eat tonight?
你们晚上打算吃什么呀
Cabbage and tofu,
白菜豆腐
and stir-fried pork.
还有炒猪肉
Go on.
去吧
Hello, Mother. Hello, Auntie Fan.
阿娘好 樊姨好
Sit.
坐
What is Changning doing at home?
长宁妹妹在家里干吗
I miss her.
我好想她
How about after New Year's Eve,
那过了除夕
you come over to our place and hang out with her?
你去我家里找她玩 怎么样
Mother, can I go?
娘 我可以去吗
Fine.
行吧
Just this once.
下不为例
Changning said
长宁妹妹说
she'd show me her family heirloom.
要带我看家里的祖传宝贝
Family heirloom?
祖传宝贝
She probably meant our butcher knife.
她说的应该是杀猪刀
I guess that won't be necessary.
这个就没必要了吧
That's so cool!
这也太棒了
So it's actually a butcher knife!
居然是杀猪刀唉
I have things to discuss with Auntie Fan.
我和你樊姨还有话要说
Go study first.
你先去读书
Let's go.
走吧
Qianqian.
浅姐
Aren't you a bit too strict with Bao'er?
你对宝儿是不是严厉了些啊
Not at all.
哪有
I just want him to succeed in life.
我只是望子成龙罢了
Changyu.
长玉
Tomorrow is New Year's Eve,
明天就是除夕
and you'll surely be swamped.
你们肯定忙得不可开交
I want to wish you in advance a smooth and happy year ahead.
我先预祝你在新的一年事事顺心
I'm not a child.
我又不是小孩
Why give me a lucky money pouch?
你给红包给我干吗
Us girls
咱们女孩子呀
are forever young.
永远年轻
Come on. Let's get a drink.
走 喝酒去
Drinking at noon?
大中午的 喝酒
We women drink when we feel like it,
这女人喝酒是看心情
not when the clock says so.
又不是看时间
If not now, then when?
此时不喝何时喝啊
Cheers!
干杯
Qianqian.
浅姐
The last time I was this happy
我上次这么快活的时候
was the day I married Yan Zheng.
还是和言正成亲那日
Changyu,
长玉
you've been married for quite some time now.
你成亲也有些时日了
That husband of yours—
你家的那位夫君啊
are you satisfied with him?
你可还满意
He's not just all show, is he?
他不会是个银样镴枪头吧
All show?
什么银样镴枪头
Yan Zheng is pure gold—
言正是金的
through and through.
十足真金
He's that good?
这么厉害
I'm going to find someone
我现在就去找人
to beat Granny Kang up.
打那个康婆子
She said you two hadn't even consummated your marriage.
她说你们根本就没圆房
You were talking about consummating the marriage?
你在说圆房啊
What else would I mean?
不然呢
Granny Kang really has a potty mouth.
康婆子那个粪坑嘴
It's fine. I'll beat her up. I can afford the damages.
没事 姐打人姐赔得起
Don't worry.
别担心啊
Qianqian.
姐
Actually...
她其实
She wasn't entirely wrong.
也没有完全说错
Which part wasn't wrong?
哪部分没说错啊
One day,
有一天
Mrs. Zhao locked the two of us in a room.
大娘把我和他关在了一个屋子里
He probably wanted to kiss me.
他应该是想亲我的
Did you eat tangerine peel candy?
你吃陈皮糖了
You smell like tangerine peel candy.
身上有一股陈皮糖的味道
Do you want some now?
你现在想吃吗
And then?
然后呢
Then...
然后
We had a fight.
我们就打了一架
So you two are actually serious?
你们俩认真的呀
Actually, I know deep down
其实我心里清楚
that
他呀
he'd leave sooner or later.
迟早是要走的
I've hinted at it several times,
我话里话外问过他好几回
yet he never gave a different answer.
他都没有改口
Your man does seem to be
你家那位看起来
too big a fish for your small pond.
的确不像个池中物
It's okay.
没事
If he insists on leaving,
他要是执意要走
just have a baby with him before he goes.
那就在他走之前跟他要个孩子
Think about it—
你想啊
if the child turns out as good-looking as him,
要是孩子跟他长得一样好看
that would be a kind of blessing too.
那也是一种福气啊
That won't do, right?
这样不行吧
Wouldn't that basically be taking advantage of him?
这不是耍流氓吗
You know the saying, "you can't catch a wolf without sacrificing a lamb."
舍不得娃套不着狼
Wait—actually, in this case it's:
不对
you won't get a baby without feeding the wolf.
是舍不得喂狼套不着娃
Don't worry.
放心
Leave this to me.
这事啊 包在姐身上
Zhao Xun, the shopkeeper of Lin'an Rice Shop, is here to visit.
林安米行掌柜赵询特来拜访
It's freezing cold.
天寒地冷
Won't Your Lordship invite me in?
侯爷不请小的进去坐坐吗
Your Lordship.
侯爷
How did you recognize me?
怎么认出我的
I used to do business in Jizhou and Yanzhou.
小的曾在霁州焉州奔走生意
I was lucky enough to have seen Your Lordship there.
有幸见过侯爷风采
So?
所以呢
Why are you here today?
今日登门所为何事
Your Xie family has always been loyal and virtuous,
谢家忠良传家
which is a fact known throughout the whole country.
举国上下众所皆知
Yet Heaven is unjust,
奈何老天不公
allowing evildoers to bring you harm.
总为奸人所害
I too feel indignation on Your Lordship's behalf.
小的也为侯爷鸣不平啊
I don't understand what you mean.
我不懂你的意思
Wasn't the reason Wei Yan hunted Your Lordship down
侯爷被魏严追杀的原因
because you were investigating
不就是因为追查
the Jinzhou Massacre from 16 years ago?
十六年前的瑾州惨案吗
Who exactly are you?
你到底是什么人
Sixteen years ago,
十六年前
in that fire at the Eastern Palace—
在东宫那场大火里
I was one of the lucky survivors.
侥幸活下来的人
Wei Yan is a treacherous official in power,
魏严奸臣当道
supporting a puppet emperor.
扶持傀儡皇帝
We are a group of people
我们是一群
who want to restore order.
想要拨乱反正之人
So,
所以
do you have any proof?
你有证据吗
Crown Prince Chengde and Your Lordship's father
当年承德太子和令尊
both died tragically in Jinzhou.
一同惨死于瑾州
Then the Emperor abdicated,
接连皇帝禅位
and the Eastern Palace caught fire.
东宫失火
All these suspicious events pointed to Wei Yan.
这一切的蹊跷都指向魏严
Your Lordship's father and the Crown Prince both died in battle,
令尊和太子一同战死沙场
and their bodies were hung on the city wall by the Beijue people for 3 days.
被北厥人挂在城楼之上暴尸三日
Doesn't Your Lordship want to avenge this blood feud?
侯爷就不想报此血仇吗
Your Lordship had just started reinvestigating the Jinzhou Massacre,
侯爷您刚开始重查瑾州惨案
and you immediately got hunted down
就引来追杀
and ended up here—
落难至此
isn't that proof enough?
这难道还不算证据
Not enough.
不够
We also found out that
我们还查明
Wei Yan sent his Suicide Warriors
魏严派手下死士
across the Capital and 17 prefectures
跨越一京十七府
to kill over 10 people—
杀了十余人
all retainers who once worked for Wei Yan
都是一些曾经替魏严做过事
and later retired.
后来归隐的家将
What exactly does the Fan family have
樊家到底有什么物什
that's worth the Wei family's Iron Suicide Warriors coming here for?
值得你们魏家玄铁死士来找
It was the Prime Minister.
是相爷
He sent me here to find a letter.
让我来找一封信
So Fan Erniu must have also worked for Wei Yan before,
所以樊二也曾替魏严做事
which is why he kept being hunted down.
才引来的频频追杀
Your Lordship.
侯爷
Wei Yan is immensely powerful now,
魏严势大
with ambitions that could overshadow the heavens.
意图遮天蔽日
To bring him down,
想要扳动他
doesn't Your Lordship need an ally?
侯爷难道不需要帮手吗
How can I trust you?
我如何才能信得过你
How can Your Lordship trust me?
侯爷如何才能信我
Give me a deposit first.
先下个定金吧
What deposit?
什么定金
200,000 piculs of grain—
二十万石粮食
how does that sound?
如何
It seems he really knows about
看来他果然知道孤
my grain collection from all across Jizhou and Chongzhou.
从霁州崇州各地征粮的事了
We bought from many sources,
我等是多方征买
with over 100 grain merchants involved.
光粮商转手就不下一百家
How did he know so accurately?
他如何知道得这么准确
I'd actually like to ask you that.
这事孤倒好想问问你了
Forgive me, Master. It was my negligence.
主子恕罪 是属下失职
But it's good that he's willing to name his terms.
不过他肯提条件就是好的
It's business, after all.
谈生意嘛
Once he quotes a price, we can talk.
开了价就能谈
200,000 piculs...
二十万石
Master,
主子
the grain from all across Chongzhou and Jizhou
这几个月崇州霁州的粮食
has almost been emptied by us these past months.
都快被我们收空了
He didn't ask you to give it all at once, did he?
也没人让你一次性给他
Father never cared about me,
父王从未把孤放在心头
and the position of Crown Prince was meant for Sui Yuanqing.
世子之位也是随元青的
But if we can gain the support of the Marquis of Wu'an,
但若我们能得武安侯助力
our chances of success will soar.
你我的胜算便会大增
What if the Marquis of Wu'an
倘若武安侯
doesn't believe your identity,
不相信主子的身份
takes the grain, and turns against us, Master?
拿了粮食却翻脸
What then?
当如何
Turn against us?
翻脸
Who else can he turn to?
他还能去哪儿啊
Can he possibly go back to work for Wei Yan?
难道能重投魏严麾下
As long as he's willing to help me wholeheartedly,
他只要肯真心实意地帮孤
let alone 200,000 piculs of grain—
别说二十万石粮
I can even grant all 4 prefectures
整个西北四府
of the Northwest to him as his fief.
孤赐给他做封地又如何
Understood.
明白
I'll see to it immediately.
那属下这就去办
Wei Yan, oh Wei Yan.
魏严啊魏严
You will soon
你很快
be bitten by the ungrateful wolf
就会被你亲手养大的白眼狼
you raised yourself.
咬上一口
Prime Minister.
相爷
I was investigating Grand Tutor Li's dealings with the rebels,
属下暗查李太傅与贼党往来之事
and I accidentally found out that when the Marquis of Wu'an
意外查出
was reinvestigating the Jinzhou cases from 16 years ago,
武安侯重查十六年前瑾州旧事
it was exactly Lord Changxin's people who plotted against him.
正是长信王府内部做的手脚
If Xie Zheng didn't exist in this world,
若这世上没有这谢征的话
Lord Changxin would have one less major threat on the battlefield.
长信王阵前就少了最大的威胁
The Sui family is
随家这是
trying to ruin my great plans.
在坏我的大事
There's one more thing.
还有一事
Li Huai'an was recalled to the Capital by Grand Tutor Li
李怀安被李太傅召回京
for some unknown reason.
不知为何
With Princess Royal back in the Capital,
长公主归京
that old coot probably wants to push the marriage,
那老匹夫想要促成婚事
so he hurried to recall his eldest legitimate grandson.
便急着召回他的嫡长孙
Just leave him be.
别管他了
Write to He Jingyuan immediately
立即书信给贺敬元
and tell him to defend Lucheng to the death.
让他死守卢城
That's the place for the decisive battle.
那里才是决战之地
Happy New Year.
过年好
Come on, everyone, time for dinner.
大家吃饭
Coming. Coming.
来了来了
Happy New Year, Mrs. Wang.
王婶过年好啊
Happy New Year, Mrs. San.
三娘给你拜年了
Happy New Year, Mr. San.
三叔过年好
Happy New Year.
过年好
Happy New Year to you.
给你拜年啊
Keep writing. Keep writing.
走 走
Horizontal.
横
Horizontal, vertical.
横竖
Vertical.
竖
Horizontal with a turn, left-falling, right-falling.
横折撇捺
Sister, Zheng is teaching me how to write.
阿姐 姐夫在教宁娘写字
Good girl.
真乖
Do you know how to write Spring Festival couplets?
你会写春联吗
My mother used to write them every year.
往年的春联都是我娘亲写的
Can you write Spring Festival couplets, Zheng?
姐夫会写春联吗
Get me the paper.
你拿纸给我吧
Okay.
好
You ground too much ink.
研多了
♪ The scenery is as clear as me ♪
那就多写几副
We can give some to Mrs. Zhao and the others,
给大娘他们几副
and we can put the rest on the doorframes of all these rooms.
再把这几个屋子的门框都贴上
For good omen.
图个喜庆
Alright.
行
D-Did I accidentally touch you?
我 我是不是碰到你了
It's fine. I just got a bit too much ink on the brush.
没事 墨蘸多了而已
Your calligraphy is really good.
写得真好
What a pity.
真是可惜了
But it's okay.
不过没事
[As ice thaws, the springs awaken] [With snow gone, new grass sprouts]
贴在我和宁娘的房间门口就好了
Ice something...
冰什么
Spring something something...
泉什么什么
Snow something... New grass sprouts.
雪 什么草 芽 生
As ice thaws, the springs awaken.
冰销泉脉动
With snow gone, new grass sprouts.
雪尽草芽生
When my mother wrote Spring Festival couplets,
我娘以前写春联的时候
she didn't like writing those
也不喜欢写那种
clichéd auspicious phrases either.
千篇一律的吉祥话
Do you like these?
你喜欢
You know how to paint?
你会作画
Only a little.
会点皮毛
That's enough.
那也够用了
If you go and sell your calligraphy and paintings out there,
你出去卖字画
you'll definitely make a lot of money.
一定能赚很多钱
I don't paint what doesn't please me.
我不作不称心意的画
I want to write something too.
宁娘也想写
Write a top scroll then.
那你写个横批吧
Come on, Changning, write a top scroll.
来 宁娘写个横批
What should you write?
写什么呢
Just write this.
就写这个吧
How's this top scroll?
这横批怎么样
Just like...
好比
Joining a dog's tail to sable fur.
狗尾续貂
That means it's very good, right?
是很好的意思吧
It's perfect.
恰到好处
I wrote it too well.
是我写得太好了
I'm amazing.
真厉害
Oh right, we're missing the falcon.
对了 还差隼隼
Good falcon,
隼隼乖
let's celebrate the New Year together.
我们一起过年
With the falcon's claw print,
印上隼隼的爪印
our family is complete.
咱们一家就整整齐齐了
Look.
看
Dear.
老头子
Lower. Lower.
往下点 往下点
Alright, alright. Right there.
好好好 好
Don't move. Don't move further. That's it.
别动了 别动了 可以了
-Alright. -Let's go check on Changyu.
行
Okay.
好
Dear.
老婆子
How is the calligraphy?
字怎么样啊
It's beautiful.
这字真好看
-I've never seen such nice calligraphy before. -He wrote this, right?
我就没见过这么好看的字
-I guess so. -You're illiterate. Can you really understand it?
是吧
I may not be able to read,
虽然说我不识字
but I can tell this calligraphy is valuable.
但我能看出这字值钱
Look how square and upright the characters are.
你看这字方方正正
So neat and proper.
规规矩矩
It's obvious it's worth a fortune.
一看就值好多钱
Mr. Zhao, Mrs. Zhao.
老赵头 赵大娘
The couplets are written so well.
这对子写得太不错了
Who wrote these?
这谁写的
Changyu's husband wrote all of these.
这些字都是长玉夫婿写的
Changyu's husband.
长玉相公
Changyu,
长玉
your husband writes really nice couplets—
你家这夫婿对联写得真不错呀
even better than the ones Scholar Song
比起往年那个宋举人写出来的
wrote in previous years.
都要好
That's why I say
要不怎么说
our Changyu has good taste.
我们长玉的眼光好呢
Can he write a pair for me too?
给嫂子也写一副行不
-Yeah. Write a pair for us too. -Write for all of us.
对呀 给我们也写一副 都写上
Sis.
嫂子
I'm sorry.
对不住啊
We ran out of red paper for the couplets.
家里没有多的春联纸了
Oh, red paper for the couplets?
那春联纸嘛
I've got plenty of red paper at home from previous years.
往年家中红纸多的是
I've got some at home too.
我们家也有
-I have some too. -Me too.
我这也有 我家也有
Alright.
行
Bring the paper over.
把纸拿来吧
Alright!
得嘞
Quick, go get the red paper.
快 快去拿红纸去
Okay, thanks.
好 谢谢啊
See you in a bit.
那咱一会儿见
Let's go.
走走走
If you aren't willing,
如果不愿意
you didn't have to agree.
可以不用应下来的
Don't worry about me.
别顾及我
I am willing.
我愿意
You just said
你方才还说
you wouldn't paint what didn't please you.
不作不称心的画
Now it pleases you?
这会儿称心了
Grind the ink.
研墨
Changyu.
长玉
Mrs. Zhuang.
庄娘子
Here's some homemade puffed rice candy—
自家做的米花糖
a little snack for Changning.
给宁儿当零食
But...
这
Take it.
拿着
Changyu, I heard your husband was writing Spring Festival couplets for people.
听说长玉你夫婿在给人写春联
Our family hasn't gotten ours written yet, either,
大娘家今年的春联还没写呢
so I boldly came along.
就厚着脸皮一起过来了
It's nothing fancy,
也没什么好东西
just some freshly ground tofu for you to taste.
现磨的豆腐带过来给你们尝尝
Ladies,
婶子们
please have a seat first.
先坐吧
Alright, alright.
好嘞 好嘞
Thank you.
谢谢了
Here's the red paper I brought.
我拿的红纸
Alright, thank you.
好嘞 谢谢
Harmony brings peace to all frontiers.
家和自秀三边静
Done.
好了
It's finished.
写完了
"Lanterns shine on homes to celebrate the prosperous year."
灯笼照户庆余年
"The ox carries spring to plow the green fields."
牛背驮春耕绿野
It means that when spring comes next year,
意思就是明年开春
there will be a bumper harvest,
五谷丰登
and the whole family will be happy and healthy.
还有全家人幸福安康
Though storm and darkness fill the sky
风雨如晦
and the rooster crows without end,
鸡鸣不已
now that I have met you—
既见君子
how could my heart not rejoice?
云胡不喜
The meaning of this poem line is that
这句诗的意思呢
amidst the gloom and pouring rain,
是说昏晦暴雨如注
the roosters crow in panic.
鸡鸣声声惶然
Yet, precisely in this chaotic moment,
偏生在这诸般乱象纷纭之际
I glance around,
眸光轻转
and I catch sight of her.
却一眼望见了她
It's like parting the clouds and mist,
就像拨开云雾
and a beam of light falls upon me—
有一束光打在了我身上
warm and radiant,
暖煦四溢
filling my heart with joy.
心生欢喜
When I heard him recite this line before,
先前听他念这话时
I just thought it sounded nice,
只觉得顺耳好听
but I had no idea what was so good about it.
却压根不晓得好在哪儿
Until just now,
直到方才
when he turned his head and looked at me.
他转过头朝我看过来
In that instant,
那一刹
the courtyard fell completely silent.
院子里静悄悄的
Even the falling snow seemed lighter,
雪花飘着都像轻了好些
and even the wind blowing over
连吹过来的风
felt softer and gentler.
都软乎乎的不刮人了
It was like the sun on the Winter Solstice—
跟冬至日头似的
neither slanting nor skewed,
不偏不斜
shining perfectly on me.
正好照在我身上
It turns out when you are truly happy,
原来人真正高兴起来
your heart sings.
心里是会响的
Just like when you sit by the stove,
就像守着灶膛烤火时
and the firewood crackles softly,
火柴 噼里啪啦的轻响
crisp and warm.
细碎又暖和
Your hand must hurt, right?
手疼了吧
It's nothing.
没事
Still toughing it out.
嘴硬
Are you here for couplets too?
你也来写对子的
Before...
以前
Before, it was always my elder grandson, Kang Dan, who wrote the Spring Festival couplets.
以前都是我那大孙子康胆儿写
But later, he got into trouble
后来他犯事了
and was sent off for forced labor.
被抓去充劳役
After that,
之后呢
Scholar Song helped out.
是宋举人帮忙
You see, Kang Dan turned 18 this year.
这不康胆儿今年十八了
He's timid and simple-minded.
胆小 憨
I just hope
我就盼着呀
that my younger grandson, Xiaohu,
我那小孙子小虎啊
could be smarter and sharper than his older brother.
比他哥能够聪明伶俐些
You know,
人哪
by the end of the year,
这一年到头呢
isn't life really just about having something to look forward to?
不就活着个盼头吗
Next year, or the year after—
明年 后年
perhaps
也许啊
things will get better.
就好了
Please sit.
坐吧
What do you want me to write?
想写什么
Just no more wars,
就是别再打仗了
so that our Kang family
给我们康家呀
could continue our line.
也留个后
And I hope my two grandsons,
我那两个孙子呀
without their parents to protect them,
没爹没娘罩着
could still grow up safe and sound.
也能平安长大
Okay.
好
Greetings, Mother.
给母妃请安
May I ask why
母妃唤儿臣前来
you summoned me here, Mother?
是为何事
It's New Year's Eve, a time for family reunion.
大年三十 阖家团圆
Do I really need a reason
母妃竟连召见你一面
just to see you?
都还需要由头不成
That's not what I meant.
儿臣不是这个意思
I wish you a prosperous New Year, Mother.
儿臣祈愿母妃新岁嘉时
May peace and health be with you always.
祥宁永驻 康泰相陪
You were betrothed to the Marquis of Wu'an since birth.
你与武安侯自小指腹为婚
Back when the Marquis of Wu'an was still around,
当初武安侯还在世时
he was a heroic young man with great military merits.
少年英姿 战功赫赫
Such a fine man would have been a great match for you,
如此好儿郎当是良配
yet you said you only saw him as an older brother
你却说与他只有兄妹之情
and refused to take him as your Prince Consort.
不愿招为驸马
And now, this failed scheme
如今却让这一场破棋局
has consumed you.
勾走了你的魂
What do you mean by that, Mother?
母妃此话何意
Ever since you returned to the palace,
自从你回宫以来
you've used illness as an excuse multiple times to put off meeting Li Huai'an.
几次三番称病推迟与李怀安见面
I have already made arrangements.
本宫已命人安排
You will go to the Lantern Festival with him on the fifteenth.
上元节你和他同游灯会
Mother!
母妃
The Gongsun family has been barred from holding office in the court for generations.
公孙家世代不得入阁
This is an imperial regulation
此乃皇家规制
and must never be defied.
断不可违逆
As the Princess Royal,
你身为长公主
you must not let that scheme
切不可因为那场棋局
ruin the grand cause of our imperial family.
便将皇家的大业毁于一旦哪
I'm not your pawn, Mother.
儿臣不是母妃的棋子
And I refuse to be manipulated in this palace scheme.
不愿被摆弄在这宫廷棋局之中
You only care about family glory
母妃心中只有家族荣耀
and imperial regulations, Mother.
皇家规制
Have you ever truly cared about my happiness or sorrow?
可曾真正顾念过儿臣的喜乐哀愁
In short, from now on,
总之日后
you must not see anyone from the Gongsun family again.
公孙家的人你一概不得再见
Just cut that thought off now.
趁早断了这心思吧
If there's nothing else, Mother,
母妃若无别的事
I shall take my leave.
儿臣先行告退
Shu!
姝儿
Your Highness, where are you going?
殿下 你去哪儿啊
I'm going to hang myself.
本宫去上吊
Do you want to join me, Nanny?
嬷嬷要不要陪着
Though loved for its clever words,
人怜巧语情虽重
the bird yearns to fly free.
鸟忆高飞意不同
Come on.
吃吧
Let's eat.
吃起来
It smells so good.
好香啊
Smells so good.
好香
Thank you. Thank you.
谢谢 谢谢
Here.
来
Yummy, yummy.
好吃好吃
Yummy.
好吃
Eat up.
快吃
Coming up.
来喽
-Happy New Year!
新年欢喜
Let's have another cup.
咱们再来一杯
Fill it up.
满上
I want some too.
我也来点
No, you're still injured.
不行 你身上有伤
This light liquor won't hurt.
这清酒不碍事
Have some tea instead.
喝点茶水
The doctor said
大夫说了
no alcohol until you recover.
痊愈之前不能沾酒
I want some too.
宁娘也要喝
Changning, you can't drink either.
宁娘也不能沾酒
Come on, have tea with Zheng.
来 跟姐夫一起喝茶水
Eat and drink well. Peace year after year.
吃饱喝好 岁岁平安
Cheers.
喝酒喝酒
Come on.
来
Yan Zheng.
言正
Why don't we...
不如我们
Fireworks!
放烟花了
Let's go watch the fireworks.
看烟花去
Come on, let's go watch the fireworks.
走走走 看烟花了
Be careful, Changning.
宁娘慢点
What did you just say?
你刚刚说什么
I didn't catch that.
我没听清
I... I said I wanted to drink more.
我 我说我还想喝酒
-Come on, let's go upstairs. -Let's go upstairs and watch.
走走走 咱们上楼
Good wine.
好酒
Don't drink too much.
别喝多了
I'm perfectly sober.
我清醒得很
This wine isn't strong at all.
这酒压根就不醉人
I'll pour you some tea.
给你倒杯茶
Sober up with some tea.
喝点茶解解酒
Looking down on me, huh?
这是看不起谁呢
My father can drink a whole jar of strong liquor,
我爹能喝一坛烧刀子
so I can handle at least half a jar.
我起码也能喝半坛
This wine isn't intoxicating at all.
这酒一点不醉人
Come on, bottoms up.
来 干了
Come on.
来
You really are drunk.
你是真的喝醉了
I'm totally fine.
一点事没有
Happy New Year.
新年欢喜
You won't get a baby
舍不得喂狼
without feeding the wolf.
套不着娃
What baby?
什么娃